Literally nothing good will come of a of
an actual war between India and Pakistan
because the Pakistanis will lose.
>> It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. The Pakistanis will
lose. That the Pentagon controlled the
Pakistani nuclear arsenal.
Heat. Heat.
The Pakistanis have come out publicly
and said that they control the nukes.
But I can tell you definitively
>> that the State Department was telling
both sides, if you're going to fight,
fight. Keep it short and keep it
non-nuclear.
If nuclear weapons are introduced, the
whole world is going to change. And so I
think there was restraint on both sides.
The Pakistanis need to come to a policy
conclusion that there's nothing positive
for them in fighting India. Nothing,
literally nothing good will come of a of
an actual war between India and Pakistan
because the Pakistanis will lose.
>> It's as simple as that. They'll lose.
And I'm not talking about nuclear
weapons. I'm talking just about a
conventional war. The Pakistanis will
lose,
>> right?
>> And so there's no benefit to constantly
provoking the Indians. At the CIA, we
called the Indian policy um strategic
patience.
The the Indian government would have
been perfectly within its rights to
respond respond by striking Pakistan and
they didn't.
And I remember at the White House,
people were saying, "Wow, the Indians
are really exhibiting a very mature
foreign policy here." We expected the
Indians to to strike back and they
didn't. And that kept the the world from
what might have been a nuclear exchange,
>> right?
>> But India's gotten to the point where
they can't risk strategic patience being
misunderstood as weakness.
>> And so they had to respond. Right
>> now the question the question now that
CIA analysts are likely asking
themselves are did the Pakistanis learn
their lesson not to keep poking the
hornets's nest and expecting to not be
stung when I was when I was stationed in
Pakistan in 2002. I was told
unofficially that that the Pentagon
controlled the Pakistani nuclear
arsenal, that Musharif had turned
control over to the United States
because he was afraid of exactly what
you just described.
But the Pakistanis in the intervening
years, and remember I was there 23
years ago, over the last 23 years, the
Pakistanis have come to say that is
absolutely not true. the United States
has nothing to do with the Pakistani
nuclear arsenal, that Pakistani generals
are the ones that control it. So I don't
know if if that's true,
then I would be very worried about who
is in charge politically in Pakistan.
>> You know, for example, for example, um
Iran Khan, I can't believe that I forgot
his name.
>> Who's in jail? A
>> Who's in jail?
>> Yes. Yeah.
>> Right. and still wildly popular.
>> Wildly. Yeah.
>> He told us when he was still the prime
minister, he said, "Listen, I've got
this political situation here
domestically. I'm going to start blaming
you for everything."
And and the ambassador laughed and said,
"We get blamed for everything anyway, so
we don't care." So everything that
happened, it was the United States
fault, and it was the US, they turned
their backs on us, and the US did this,
and the US did that, and then they
arrested him anyway.
So he got a message out to the US
government saying can you help me get
out of this and we went to Jamaima
Goldmid his gold whatever her name was
ex-wife
>> and she went to Pakistan and asked them
if they would release him and they said
no.
So like you, I'm worried about continued
disagreement in Pakistani politics that
has the potential to spill into the
streets because the Pakistanis have a
tendency to get themselves spun up
>> and people die during demonstrations and
there are attacks against political
figures and assassinations and and uh
and the country is not known for its uh
transformative you know leaders making
positive decisions.
>> [music]